[Birds chirping]
[Men yelling]
[Man whistles]
- Come on! Come on, now!
[Horse whinnying]
- [Man yelling]
- Ho! ho! Ho, ho!
- It's been almost a year
since I left my home in the east
and traveled west
with the man I loved.
I was positive about my future--
full of hopes and dreams.
Our eyes were always
on the end of the trail,
as if life as I
visi
would be just that.
In fact, if someone had told me
that I would find myself here
today,
I would have called them crazy.
I was sure of myself
and where I was headed,
stubborn, full of pride.
I was in control.
Or so I thought.
- Quit acting like a kid, Marty.
Get back here.
- No.
Not until you admit
that I am right
and head this way.
- We're going
in the right direction.
- We're going north!
- Mr. Graham said to go north.
- He said to go northwest.
Don't you think it's strange
we haven't come upon it yet?
- Well, we'd be there already
if the weight of these books
hadn't slowed us down!
- Those books will provide us
with a little culture
once we get settled.
- Oh, well, it's just too bad
we can't eat
any of that culture.
- Ugh!
- That 200 pounds
of beans and rice
that we had to toss off
the wagon to lessen the weight
would taste a whole lot better
right now
than the 200 pounds of books
we got!
- None of this
would have happened
if you hadn't talked me into
coming out here
to the middle of nowhere,
Aaron claridge!
- [Laughing] we both know
that you don't do anything
you don't want to do.
- [Sighs]
- For once in your life,
be reasonable!
- I'm tired.
Sick and tired of the dirt
and miles
that seem to lead nowhere
and the layers of dust
on my skin.
Aching feet, aching back.
If I never sit in that wagon
again,
it will be all right by me.
[Horse snorts and whinnies]
- Marty.
- I see.
[Giggles]
- It's exactly like
i pictured it.
Can you see it?
Just over there.
- A cabin.
With curtains in the windows.
- A-a-and over here,
a barn!
- And a garden, where we'll grow
our own food.
- Those trees are just made
for swings for all those kids
who are gonna look
just like their momma.
- I don't mind
if they look like their father.
- We did it.
[Laughs]
We actually did it, Marty.
This just feels right,
doesn't it?
This will be the perfect place
to raise a family.
Pass down the land
to our children
and give them opportunities
that are limitless.
- We can do anything,
as long as we're together.
- [Laughing]
- oh! [Laughing]
- Promise me...
That even if things get rough,
we'll remind each other of that,
ok?
- I promise.
- Dadblameit!
Marty.
One of the horses got away.
- Oh no, Aaron.
- I'm taking the other horse,
and I'm going after him.
Shouldn't be gone too long.
He's probably just a ways
down the stream.
- I'm coming with you.
- No need.
I'll be back with that horse
before breakfast.
Make up a lot of pancakes.
I'll be hungry.
[Horse whinnies]
Got ya.
[Horse whinnying]
Hya!
Come on!
Hya, come on! Let's go!
Hya!
Come on!
Come on, let's go!
Hya, hya!
[Horse neighing]
Uh!
[Softly] Marty.
[Horse whinnies]
- Ho! whoa.
Mrs. claridge, Ben.
Ben Graham, ma'am?
Met you a couple days back.
Found him about an hour ago.
- [Marty breathes shakily]
- Mrs. claridge.
Can I get you some water?
Ma'am!
[Stifled crying]
Mrs. claridge?
I guess you'll be needing
time to...
To think, uh...
My wife will see
to your husband.
The preacher's leaving tomorrow.
I can bring him back here
first thing in the morning,
say a few words.
Oh.
[Wind blowing]
- We're fine.
We're fine.
We're fine. We're fine.
[Howling]
We're fine.
- [Clearing throat] Hello?
Mrs. claridge?
Marty?
It's me...
Sarah Graham, Ben's wife.
You met me a couple days ago.
[People talking indistinctly]
Marty.
It's time.
We need to start
your husband's funeral.
We don't want to be starting it
without ya.
- [Whimpers]
I can't do this.
- You have to do this.
- I would--
I would appreciate just--
just a moment, please.
- We'll wait.
- [Whimpers]
- Aaron claridge
journeyed west
in search of a dream.
His untimely death means
that one journey is over
and another has just begun.
[Low chatter]
- [Sighs]
- Winter's coming,
and there's no wagon train
heading east 'til spring.
I don't know how you're fixed
for money to board in town,
but...
[Sighs] you're gonna have to
make a decision, and soon.
[Sighs] well...
You take tonight
and think on it,
and Ben will come check on you
tomorrow.
- Thank you.
[Thunder rumbling]
- Excuse me, ma'am.
I'm Clark Davis...
And I'm truly sorry
about your loss.
I have a proposition for you.
I know it's not the right place
or the right time.
But I figure if we marry,
it'll help solve
both our problems.
You'll have a roof
over your head,
and all your needs will be met.
And my missie?
Well, she'll have a mama.
I know it sounds-- crazy.
And the timing's unlikely.
But you have to understand,
the preacher's leaving the area
today,
and he's not gonna be back
until spring.
And I ask this...
Only for my daughter.
I'm thinking...
That she needs a woman's hand...
In parts of her life.
I know it's not
the perfect solution,
but when the wagon train
heads back east in the spring...
I'll pay the passage
so you can go home.
- You'll help me get home?
- If that's what you want.
I'll leave you to think on it,
ma'am.
[Kids yelling]
[Men talking indistinctly]
- Come on, get up!
- Hey!
- Pa, I tried to stop them.
- Hey, hey!
Missie!
Hey! hey, come here!
- [Panting]
he started it, pa.
- Come here, you get up.
Get up!
- Clint says I got a new ma.
He's lyin' to me.
- Is that true, Clint?
- No, sir.
She poked me right in the nose
for no good reason.
- You're a liar!
That is so a good reason.
- Hey! where do you think
you're going?
- Uh!
- Apologize.
- Sorry.
- What did I tell you
about fighting with girls?
- I ain't fightin' with no girl.
It's just missie.
- [Sighs] get inside. Go on.
No worries.
- Come on, missie.
We need to talk.
What are you upset about?
You all right? Huh?
- I don't want to do this.
I just want to go home.
- Now, you listen to me.
There's no place
in this part of the country
to waste your time
cryin' over wants.
Your life's about needs now.
You need a roof over your head
for the winter.
Now, that's
what you bargained for.
- We are here today,
gathered in the lord's name,
to join this man and this woman
in marriage.
Please join hands.
Will you, Clark Davis,
take Marty claridge to be
your lawful wedded wife?
- I will.
- [Whimpering]
- And will you, Marty claridge,
take Clark Davis to be
your husband?
- Come on, now, let's go.
- Just answer "i will."
- I will.
- Then I pronounce you
man and wife.
- [Dog barking]
- Buddy. come here, buddy.
- I'll bring in your trunk.
[Chicken clucking]
[Clears throat]
This is the bedroom
you and missie will be sharing.
I'll get my things
moved into the lean-to.
[Crickets chirping]
[Owl hooting]
- Morning.
[clears throat]
Saved you some ham.
I'm--I'm not much of a cook,
but it's usually pretty filling.
- I've never seen nobody
sleep so long.
I thought she might be dead.
- Missie...
Go and wait for me
in the wagon.
[Sighs]
Got some things
i need to tend to.
I'll be taking missie with me.
[Clears throat]
I won't be back 'til supper.
Bye.
Hya! hya!
- [Crying]
[Crying]
[Door squeaks]
[Footsteps]
- She's sleeping again.
- Mm-hmm.
Let's go have our supper.
- Pa...
Is she all right?
- No.
But she will be.
Come on.
- [Sighs]
[Horse whinnying]
- [Gasps]
[Horse neighs]
- Come on!
Come on! Come on!
Come on!
And bless this dear child
in her time of grief.
And bless this food before us,
and we thank you for
the fine day ahead of us, amen.
- You got an awful lot
of pretty dresses.
Seems like you got
an awful lot of fancy things
that aren't good for
much anything at all.
- We fetched your wagon
for you yesterday,
and we brought it into the barn.
- What are you going to do
with all them books?
- I checked to see if there was
any food that would spoil
when I was stacking up
your things.
- We planned on buying supplies
as soon as we found our land.
- The books must be
pretty important to you.
I'll see if we can find
space for them in the cabin.
- [Sighs] I'm not sure
what you're expecting from me.
- Come with me.
[Cow mooing]
Missie's 9 years old.
She works almost as hard
as I do, sun up to sun down.
Has been
for the last couple years.
She never complains.
But the work is stealing
her childhood.
She doesn't know
what she's missing.
But I do.
Maybe if somebody's there
to share the chores,
she'd have time to learn
some of the things
i think you could teach her...
Things she'd learn
from her mother.
- And when I go home
in the spring?
- [Sighs]
I figure I'll cross that bridge
when I come to it.
- The books.
How did you know they were mine
and not Aaron's?
- Oh, well, a man would have
thrown them off the wagon
at the first big hill
unless he was trying to please
a stubborn woman.
[Chicken clucking]
- Why are you here?
- [Sighs]
I thought you could use
some help.
What would you like me to do?
- You may need a place to stay,
but I don't need a mother.
Pa and me been doing just fine.
- I'm a little unsure
about what to do.
Why don't you show me
how to get those eggs out
from underneath their...
You know.
- Their rears?
[Sighs]
- Spell "cow."
- K-a...
- Close. it's c-o-w.
- Gertie don't care if I know
how to spell "cow" or not.
- Gertie doesn't care,
but I do.
And so does your pa.
So, let's try another one.
Spell "fun."
- F...
[Cow moos]
[Sighs]
How do you spell "warm"?
- Warm? w-a-r-m.
- I think you better
w-a-r-m your hands.
- What?
- Well, how do you expect gertie
to give you good milk
when you're freezing her
like that?
Can probably spell "milking,"
but you sure can't do it.
How'd you get to be so old
without not knowing
how to do nothin'?
- [Breathing heavily]
[Marty straining]
[Gasps]
[Grunts]
- Oops! I really didn't mean to.
- I know exactly what you're
meaning to do, missie!
Now, you listen to me!
- You're not my mother, and i
don't have to listen to you!
- As long as I am here--
- I don't want you here!
- I've got news for you!
I don't want to be here either.
But the fact of the matter is
I made a bargain
with your father,
and I intend to keep
my end of that bargain,
even if you do everything
short of trying
to kill me in the process.
So, the way I see it,
if I can survive traveling
for months in a covered wagon,
losing my husband,
marrying a complete stranger,
I can survive you.
- So, how was your day?
- Fine.
- yeah, fine.
- [Clears throat]
I ran into Ben and Sarah Graham
in town today,
and they were asking after you.
- That was kind of them.
- Actually, they invited us all
to their annual get-together.
- Is it already time?
- It is.
You see, the grahams
have a party this time of year
so folks can get together
before they're stuck inside
for the winter.
We'd understand it if, you know,
you weren't up for a party.
But it's up to you.
- Yeah. you probably
wouldn't like it.
There's tons of people
you won't know.
You'd probably just like
staying home better.
Don't you think, pa?
- I think I will go.
- Good.
[Knocking]
- What is it?
- I just need to talk to you.
- Missie's asleep,
and I'm ready for bed.
Can't we talk tomorrow?
- Well, that's just it.
I won't be here tomorrow.
I'm-- I'm leaving before sun-up.
Going to help our neighbor.
- Fine.
- Wait, it's--
- what else?
- I'll be leaving missie
here with you.
- That is why I'm here.
- Yeah, I, you know,
I just wasn't sure
if you were up to dealing
with a spirited--
- I'm fine.
Something else?
- No-- yeah.
I'll be back by supper.
- Fine. goodnight.
- Good-- night.
- [Sighs]
missie?
Missie?!
[Cow mooing]
Missie, answer me!
Where are you?!
Missie?
[Sighs]
Missie!
- You better get out of here.
- [Sighs]
Why don't you come down
so we can get to work.
- Ok.
Just as soon as he leaves.
- He?
- [Gasps]
Just come down slowly.
I've read that they won't spray
unless they feel threatened.
- You read that
in one of your books?
- Uh-huh.
- And you believe it?
- I do.
- Well, not me.
I'm starving, and I gotta use
that outhouse somethin' fierce.
But I'm not coming down.
[Barking]
- buddy, no!
- [Screams]
[Dog whimpering]
[Gasps and coughs]
Oh! Oh!
- Guess he felt threatened.
- Uh.
Ugh!
Are you sure this is going
to take the smell away?
- More or less.
Some of it's just going to
have to wear off.
- Mmm. mmm.
- [Wolf howling]
- The fire's dyin'.
- Could you...?
- I ain't supposed to.
I could burn myself.
- [Sighs]
- Something's burning.
- Oh no.
Oh!
Oh! dagblammit!
Ouch!
- Let me help you.
Hold on. Hold on.
Hold on. Missie, get me
some butter, would you?
Come on, sit down.
- It's fine.
- No. You sit down here.
I'm going to wrap it up now.
- [Moans]
- Oh, here.
Thank you.
- It's nothing, really.
- Ok. here now.
This will just take
some of the sting out.
- [Sighs]
- The pancakes are all burnt.
- Here you go.
Like that.
You know, you'll get the hang
of that stove.
It just takes
a little practice, that's all.
[Clears throat]
So, where'd the skunk find you?
- The barn.
- Better get
some more tomatoes, pa.
Took almost a whole bushel
to get her smelling this good.
- Well, I'll see what we've got
for supper in the icebox.
Missie, why don't you go ahead
and stoke that fire.
I'll try to get all the things
on your list for you
while I'm in town.
You sure you don't want
to go with us?
- No!
She said she don't.
- Doesn't.
- Hope you can make something
better than burnt pancakes.
Too bad I'll be gone,
'cause I can make
some real good fried chicken.
I'm ready, pa.
- Mm-hmm.
We'll see you soon.
[Clicking tongue]
- How hard can it be?
[Sighs]
If a child can do this,
i can do this.
Come here, chickie.
Come here.
Ugh! ugh! Ugh!
Come here! Come here!
Dagblammit!
[Sighs]
[Grunts]
[Chicken clucking]
"Pull feathers out
with the grain."
You better be worth it.
- Huh.
[laughs]
- Looks like a coyote
got in there.
- More like a wild woman
with an axe.
- Good. you're back.
Supper's ready.
- You made fried chicken.
Good, because I was getting
awful sick of pan--
- [clears throat]
- [Blows]
me too.
- Sure won't want to
have to wash all that.
- I left half my things at home.
- It's kind of wasteful,
don't you think?
- Wasteful?
- To have so many.
You can only wear
one dress at a time.
- Surely you must have
some dresses of your own.
- One for when the reverend
passes this way
and holds a service.
Like I said,
you can only wear one dress--
- at a time.
- My mama made beautiful quilts.
Hers would put
this here pattern to shame.
She made quilts
for all the neighbors
when they had their babies.
- I'm sure
they appreciated that.
- Folks loved my mama,
especially my pa.
That's why his eyes ain't
sparkly like they used to be.
- She certainly was beautiful.
- She was the prettiest thing
you ever saw.
Everybody said so.
- You must miss her very much.
- [Blows]
- [Shivers]
[Gasps]
Oh, lord!
- [Gasps]
- I'm sorry.
[Screams] ow!
- [Gasps] oh!
- Ooh!
Uh!
- [Gasps]
- [Groans]
[Sighs]
- Where's your father going?
- On his Sunday walks.
It's his time to be alone
and talk to the lord.
- I bet he has a lot to
talk to him about this morning.
- What'd you say?
- I think I'll take
a little walk of my own.
You all right here by yourself?
- I picked this dress
because I know pink is
your favorite color.
I love it when you wear pink,
mama.
You always look so pretty.
There. letting in the sun
will make you feel better.
[Sighs]
I-- I don't know why they didn't
let me come here, mama,
because I would have sat here
just like this.
And I wouldn't have made you
tired or sad.
I just wanted to tell you
that I loved you.
[Sniffs]
And I miss you.
- [Crying]
- You were spying on me!
- No.
- You're lying, I saw you.
You were watching.
How could you do that?
- Missie, I didn't mean
to be there.
But I do know
what you're feeling.
- Don't say that!
You don't know nothin'!
- I do want to help you.
- I don't want your help!
I hate it that you're here.
I was fine before you came.
I wish it was spring
so you would leave.
- I didn't mean to. I--
I was cold. I--
I didn't mean to walk in on her
like that.
- I know what you mean.
I mean, about last night, I...
I'm sorry.
I didn't mean to walk--
- I don't know
what I was thinking.
I can't stay here.
- Why?
- why?
That little girl hates me.
You were right.
She does need a mother,
but I'm not the right person.
She doesn't know it,
but she's still grieving.
- That's why you're
the right person.
- It's just not going well.
- It's going just the way
i thought it would.
I mean, I knew
she wouldn't like it at first.
- Then why put her through this?
- Because I love her.
And she needs more
than I can give her.
- Seems like an awful lot
of trouble to go through
for just a few months of lessons
and letters and sewing.
- Nothing's a waste of time
that adds to the person
that you are.
And I'm counting on the fact
that knowing you is going to add
to the person
that missie will become.
I know you can find a way
to get through to her.
- How do you know?
- Because that's
what I prayed for.
- [Sighs]
Maybe I will.
- Mm.
- We're ready.
- You look beautiful, missie.
- [Laughs]
thanks, pa.
- [Mouthing words]
[Distant conversations]
Whoa!
Whoa.
- Gonna catch flies
with your mouth hanging open
like that.
- [Gasps]
- When are you expecting?
- February.
How did you know?
- When Ellen
was expecting missie,
she'd hold onto her belly,
like you just did.
- Oh.
I was going to tell you.
The baby won't be a problem,
and I'm sure
it won't change the fare
for when I go home
in the spring.
You must be thinking
i should have told you.
- Actually, I was thinking
I'm glad
you're going to have
a little one.
To remember him by.
- And the lat--
[Sighs]
I-y...y-g...
Wag-oul.
- Keep trying to sound it out.
- In the...Wagon.
- Good.
- Tired of trying.
It's too hard,
and I don't need to read anyhow.
- Ok, fine.
- You don't care if I do it?
- No. not if you don't like
adventures.
- Reading ain't no adventure.
- Once you can read,
you can have every adventure
you ever dreamed of.
In the pages of a book,
you are...
A Princess in a tower
or the best shot in the west.
In those pages,
there are no limits
to where you can go,
who you can be.
No one will ever tell you you're
too young to slay the dragon,
because it all happens
right here where it's safe.
- [Sighs]
I guess it wouldn't hurt none
to practice a little bit more.
- I'll be back.
- Ok, pa.
- I think a walk
will do me good as well.
- [Singing in the distance]
♪ Boundless treasure ♪
♪ from my lord's
unchanging love ♪
♪ oh, to grace
how great a debtor ♪
♪ daily I'm constrained to be ♪
- [stifles laughter]
- ♪ Let thy grace,
lord, like a fetter ♪
♪ bind my wandering heart
to thee ♪
♪ prone to wander, lord,
i feel it ♪
♪ prone to leave
the god I love ♪
♪ take my heart,
oh, take and seal it ♪
♪ seal it for thy courts above ♪
[Horse neighs]
- Aaron?
[Wind howling]
[Dog barking]
- Pa!
- Winter's coming on with
the subtlety of a snakebite.
It's white out.
- Where's Marty?
- Isn't she here?
- She went walking
about when you did.
- If I'm not back here
in 10 minutes, you use the gun.
You open the door
with two hands,
raise it above your head.
You keep firing
until you see me, all right?
Whatever you do,
you don't leave that door.
Come here. It's all right.
It's going to be fine.
Going to be fine.
I'll be right back.
Marty!
Marty?!
Marty.
[Horse whinnies]
[Gunshot]
[Clicks]
- [Panting]
- Ah!
- Pa?
- She's all right.
Go back to sleep.
- Well, what about the baby?
- The baby's fine, ok?
Go on and get some rest.
[Birds tweeting]
- He should never have gone
after that horse.
It's as simple as that.
[Turkey gobbling]
- Thank you, father,
for this food
and this shelter
and this companionship.
And as we come into the season
of the birth of your son,
please make our hearts
thankful that he came, amen.
- [Sighs]
I love Christmas.
And I already know
what I'm going to make you, pa.
- Is it something I can wear?
- [Sighs]
he's always trying to trick me
into telling him.
But I'm smarter than that.
- Yes.
- So what do you do to get ready
for Christmas at your house?
- Well, about a week
before Christmas,
we go to Franklin's
and pick out a nice pine tree.
- There's pine trees
growing in the city?
- No. it's a tree lot.
Someone has already
cut them down.
- You don't get to pick
your own tree
and see which one
smells the best,
which one looks
the prettiest in the snow?
- Not exactly.
But we find one we like,
then someone delivers it to us.
Then we add to
our ornament collection
by going to purcell's store.
They have the most beautiful
glass balls
and red ribbons
to put on the tree.
We make hot cocoa,
drink it by the fire.
- And then your pa
reads you a Christmas story?
- Um, no.
- Why not?
- Well, it just wasn't
something that we did.
- Christmas without
a Christmas story.
Well, when you get back,
you have to tell him
to read it to you.
- My father passed away
a couple years ago.
- What about your mama?
- Actually, she's...
Gone too.
- So who will you spend
Christmas with
when you get back home?
- Well, I used to have it
with Aaron, of course.
I have an aunt
that I'm close to.
And I have friends there,
you know, back home.
You can certainly have Christmas
with your friends, can't you?
I mean,
there's no hard, fast rule
that it has to be with family.
- Well, you'll have
your baby now.
You could spend Christmas
with it and--
- missie, [clears throat]
Supper's getting cold.
How about a little less talking
and a little more eating?
Anyway, the joy of the season
is-- it's a gift.
It's right there for everybody,
right for the taking.
Doesn't matter
where you spend it
or-- or who you spend it with.
- [Laughs]
- Oh! [laughs]
- 1, 2, 3. We got it.
We got it.
- Then she said, "your majesty,
please tell me, your majesty,
would you like to eat some?"
- [Laughs]
- Put it around.
- This?
- That's right. Ok, good.
Good.
And as you probably can guess
right about now...
- Merry Christmas, pa.
- Merry Christmas.
- Oh!
[Laughs]
- merry Christmas.
- Thanks, pa.
- I love you.
- [Gasps]
- "There came wise men
from the east to Jerusalem.
"Where is he that is born
the king of Jews?
"For we have seen his star gazed
"and have come to worship him.
When herod the king
heard these things..."
- Marty?
- hmm?
- Where did this baby come from?
- Well, you know, from--
hasn't your pa ever told you?
- No.
- Maybe you should ask him.
- Don't you know
where your own baby come from?
- "Came from."
And, yes, of course I do.
[Sighs]
well, it's the same as you.
My husband Aaron
loved me so much,
it spilled over
and made a baby.
- What spilled over?
- It.
- what's it?
- The love.
I think that button
is still loose.
- Wow.
- What?
- Just thinking about
all the brothers and sisters
Clint has,
there's been a lot of love
spilling over at the grahams'.
- Indeed.
- I wonder if my pa
could ever feel that way
about someone again.
- He could, I guess.
Give me your hand.
Feel.
- What's that?
- That is someone who's getting
pretty impatient
to get out and meet you.
- Marty?
- I thought it was just
back pain that I was having,
but now I'm not so sure.
[Sighs]
- Are you having regular pains?
- Just starting to.
- Oh.
- I think it's time.
- I'm going to go get missie.
- There is no way
i am letting you be my--
my midwife!
Find someone else!
- There ain't no time for that.
- "Isn't"!
And it's ok.
I'll make time.
Did you deliver missie?
- No, no. There was Sarah.
- But pa's delivered
plenty of cows.
- That's good.
I feel so much better.
- I'm going to need
plenty of hot water.
Now, you run out to the barn
and get my shears.
We'll need to sterilize them.
- No, missie, missie!
Don't you dare!
- Go on.
- I would rather give birth
in a field
than have you in here!
- Birth is a--
is a natural event, Marty.
- Oh, you feel what I'm feeling
and tell me how natural it is!
Now, get out!
[Gasps] oh god,
i can't do this alone.
Please help me.
Please, please, help me.
[Distant moaning]
- Push. you're doing fine.
You're doing fine.
Push, push.
- Oh!
- Come on, push.
- [Screams]
- You're doing fine.
You're doing fine, Marty.
Come on.
[Baby crying]
- It's a boy.
Come here.
- You were more louder
than gertie
when her baby came out.
- [Laughs]
- Have you got a name?
- Aaron Luke.
Aaron after his father.
Luke after mine.
It's amazing, isn't it?
- What's that?
- This.
A powerful love
that just sweeps over you.
- It's amazing.
[Baby gurgling]
[Birds chirping]
Weather's mighty tempting.
- I thought the fresh air
might do us both some good.
- Yeah. you warm enough?
- Mm.
- He seems to be enjoying it.
- [Laughs]
- Hey.
[Horse whinnies]
It looks like
we have company coming.
- Pa?
- Go ahead.
You can do your chores later.
- Whoa, whoa.
- Hi, Clint.
Let's go play.
- Ho!
- Howdy.
- Ben, Sarah. Welcome.
- You're looking
a little more rested
since the last time
i paid a visit.
- I can hardly believe
he's already a month old.
It just doesn't seem possible.
- [Laughs] yeah, they grow
when you're not looking.
Blink, and you just might
miss it.
- That's what Clark said
about missie.
- Clark understands
and appreciates that.
He seems to be right fond
of little Aaron.
- I think he is.
- [Sighs]
I bet little Aaron
has you thinking on his pa
a lot lately, huh?
- He would have been so happy
and proud to have a son.
- Babies are
a testament to love.
They're living proof
of what you and your husband
share together.
Nobody can e
r change that.
[Chuckles]
I still see Laura's dad
every time her curls
are bouncing in the wagon.
- Ben had blonde curls?
- Not Ben, Marty.
Laura's daddy.
He was my first husband,
Thornton.
I was a widow.
I had two little ones.
When I met Ben Graham,
he had 2 young'uns of his own.
I guess you might say
we joined forces
out of sheer need.
- But, Sarah, I...
You and Ben, I just assumed
you loved each other.
- Oh, we do...
Now.
I got more love in my heart
for that man
than anybody
ought to be allowed.
I can't even tell you
when it happened.
You know, sometimes
love isn't fireworks.
Sometimes,
love just comes softly.
[Door opening]
- If you two
are through gabbing,
it's time we best
be getting home.
- I will come when I'm
good and ready, Ben Graham.
- That's fine then.
Can't say for sure
if the buggy will still be here
when you're ready.
Enjoy your pie.
[Both women laugh]
- Ornery old goat.
- [Laughs]
- [Grunts]
- Oh! [screams]
No! oh my gosh!
Please, stop!
[Laughs]
Stop! stop!
- [Laughs]
- Pa! pa!
- Stop.
- You got your laugh back.
- [Laughs]
- I think I did.
[Baby crying]
- Aaron's crying.
- Marty! Marty!
- What?
- barn's on fire.
Stay with the children.
[Horse neighing]
- Oh, please god...
If you're really there listening
to me, take care of Clark.
Please let him come out
all right.
[Horses whinnying]
Please god.
[Cow mooing]
- Come on, come on! Hya!
- Marty, what's happening?
- [Gasps]
Marty...
You realize you lost your wagon
and all your possessions
in the fire?
- I know.
- I made you a promise
last fall,
and I intend to keep it.
I'll be going into town soon
to replace that feed.
And, if you're wanting to,
we can see about
your way home.
- We should put some ointment
on your hands and wrap them
so they won't get infected.
Here's some coffee.
- Thank you.
- What are you going to do?
- Neighbors have offered
to collect some logs
and raise a new barn.
Ben said he'd take care
of the milk cow,
feed her in exchange
for some milk.
So I'll get my feed
built back up.
I think it's going to be fine.
I pretty much got it
worked out.
Just keep praying for answers.
- Why do you think
he'll answer your prayers?
- He always answers my prayers.
- Really?
did you pray for this?
- Marty--
- did you pray to have
Ellen taken away from you?
Did you pray that little missie
would grow up never knowing
her real mother?
I just don't understand
why the god that you pray to
would let such unthinkable
things happen to decent people.
- Come with me.
- Where?
what about the children?
- Oh, missie can watch Aaron
for a little while.
- Where are we going?
- We're going to church.
- Huh.
- [Sighs]
Missie could fall down
and hurt herself
even if I'm walking
right there beside her.
But that doesn't mean
that I allowed it to happen.
She knows, with a father's
unconditional love,
I'll pick her up,
and I'll carry her.
I'll try to heal her.
I'll cry when she cries.
And I'll rejoice
when she is well.
In all the moments of my life,
god has been right there
beside me.
The truth of god's love
is not that he allows
bad things to happen.
It's his promise
that he'll be there with us...
When they do.
I'm going to go back
to the cabin.
Do you want to stay a while?
All right.
♪ ♪
- Missie?
Would you do me a favor
and get your pa's dirty clothes?
- Get. would you get?
Yes, ma'am, I will.
- Oh, lord.
- Morning.
- Good morning.
- Smells good.
Excuse me.
That wet winter we had
sure did make the ground soft
for planting.
I haven't seen you
turn a page for 30 minutes.
- I can't seem to concentrate.
- Yeah.
I'm going over
to the grahams' tomorrow.
I'm going to help Ben
brand his new calves.
Do you want to come along
and visit with Sarah?
- I don't think so.
I should probably
spend the day packing.
It's about that time.
- Are you sure?
I'll let missie know.
[Clears throat]
Missie, come here.
- Ok, pa.
- I need to talk to you.
You know Marty's leaving...
...i want you to go
say goodbye.
- No, she can't go.
I don't want her to go.
[Crying]
she can't. No, no.
- Missie.
Everything seems to be
in order.
You'll be leaving shortly.
- Would you?
[Baby gurgling]
I wish I didn't have to leave.
- Then stay.
- I just can't.
I want you to have my books.
And this.
My mother gave it to me.
I might be leaving,
but my love is staying here
with you.
Please say goodbye
to Sarah and Ben for me.
I'll always be grateful
that you were there that day.
I don't know
what I would have done.
Goodbye.
Bye.
Might as well get my things
moved out of the lean-to.
- Ok.
Father...
I don't know why
you brought Marty into my life
only to have her leave
like this.
I know I don't always
understand your plan.
But I ask you
with a shattered heart,
please help me to accept it.
[Crying]
Amen.
Missie!
I'm going to bring Marty back.
You don't leave the cabin.
I'll be back as soon as I can!
[Horse galloping]
Hya! hya!
Come on! Come on!
[Whistling]
- I'm glad to be leaving
this godforsaken part
of the country.
- I wouldn't call it
godforsaken.
- Horrible snowstorms.
- Beautiful sunsets.
Rich soil.
- A woman has to be crazy
to stay.
Crazy...
Or in love.
- [Whistling]
ho! ho!
Marty! Marty!
Marty!
- What's going on?
Who's Marty?
- [Gasps]
- Hold up, boss!
[Horse whinnying]
Hold it now!
- Clark, what are you doing?
- A man loses his woman,
he goes after her.
It's as simple as that.
- I thought you wanted me to go.
- I didn't see the note.
- You didn't try to stop me.
- Until today.
[Breathing heavily]
Don't leave.
Stay with us.
Stay with me. Please.
- But I have to stay
for the right reasons.
- Stay because I love you.
I-- I love you.
- Well, maybe I should stay
because I love you.
- [Sighs]
that's a good reason, too.
Whoa.
- Mama...